DES Action USA records, 1939-2016 (bulk 1975-2014)
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES V. OUTREACH (1957-2016), 2.3 linear feet
  The lived experience of DES Action USA members and their families is documented within the folders of essays and correspondence that close the Writing sub-subseries. There are pieces by Martha and Pat Cody; Patricia Sipes, a professor at Smith College; author Anna Quindlen; and novelist Laurie Halse Anderson, from the years before her fiction career. Finally, there is a folder of anonymized requests for information from members and from the public. Some of these letters were excerpted in Cody's book, while others were printed in the DES Action Voice. These essays and correspondence record an array of health effects and psychological stress experienced by three generations of DES families.
  Women who took DES during pregnancy have felt guilt and fear for their children, in addition to anxiety about possible health effects for themselves. Those exposed in utero have experienced a wide range of health effects: cancer and radical surgeries for treatment; reproductive system malformation, and subsequent infertility and pregnancy complications; and a myriad of rarer effects, including skeletal problems, immune disorders, sexual and gender identity questions. As DES Grandchildren have been born and grown, third generation effects have been reported as well. Some third-generation issues have been the results of premature birth, while other problems include reproductive system problems (except for cancer) among other concerns. See the Survey Research sub-subseries within the Medical Professionals subseries as well as issues of DES Action Voice in the Publications sub-subseries for other personal stories.
  The last subseries in OUTREACH consists of material created for medical professionals. The lack of medical education about DES and the DES-exposed, and the subsequent neglect or outright disbelief from physicians about patient experiences has created persistent difficulties for accurate and appropriate medical care and guidance. In the face of absent outreach and education from the FDA or other medical organizations, DES Action USA has responded via the numerous educational efforts documented here.
  This subseries includes two sub-subseries: Provider Education and Survey Research. Also included in this subseries is an album of medical and news articles documenting the history of diethylstilbestrol. Provider Education contains scripts for educational slide shows, informational booklets for clinicians on treatment guidelines for DES-exposed patients, and formal curricula designed for medical students. There is material created with government funding, including continuing medical education materials from the Centers for Disease Control DES Update public education contract in 2003. See the Health Education Contracts subseries for related materials for that contract and others. The slides that accompany the scripts are located in SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS. There are also photographic prints of some of the slides. The last sub-subseries, Survey Research, contain draft surveys, correspondence, and result summaries for two health surveys conducted among members-a 2003 third-generation health effects questionnaire and a health history survey for DES Children. Raw questionnaire replies are part of the restricted SERIES VIII. MEDICAL CORRESPONDENCE AND RESEARCH DATA.
- SERIES VI. DIETHYLSTILBESTROL SUBJECT FILES (1939-2006), 0.63 linear ft.
  The DIETHYLSTILBESTROL SUBJECT FILES series contains diethylstilbestrol-related material created by organizations other than DES Action USA. Material types include advertisements, correspondence, medical literature, press releases, and comment submissions in response to FDA requests. Each subseries is arranged chronologically. The Consumer Health subseries contains campaign material by Public Citizen, a Washington, D.C. public advocacy group, concerning the use of diethylstilbestrol as an emergency contraceptive. This use of DES is one DES Action USA chose not to focus on, given the larger problem of in utero exposure, but it adds context to other controversies surrounding the drug. The subseries Medical Research contains two substantial bibliographies of research literature about DES, as well as a selection of journal articles and other medical literature, like prescription information sheets.
  The Pharmaceutical Companies subseries was primarily arranged by board members. Focusing largely on Eli Lilly, the principal manufacturer of diethylstilbestrol, this subseries contains advertisements, correspondence, press releases, and news articles about Lilly and drug company misbehavior. Several folders document a protest action arranged in response to Eli Lilly's sponsorship of the "Achievement Awards in Women's Health" to be given to several members of Congress and researchers. Despite short notice, a national letter-writing campaign began, and DES Action USA was able to persuade three members of Congress, Rep. Pat Schroeder (D-CO), Rep. Olympia Snowe (R-ME), and Rep. Henry Waxman (D-CA) to decline the awards. At the awards ceremony, DES Action USA members held a protest, which garnered press coverage.
  The last subseries, Federal Government, consists of government documents: Congressional hearings testimony, Food and Drug Administration rulings, and National Institutes of Health study proposals and records. The subseries is arranged by agency or part of Congress; it is then arranged chronologically within each section. The Food and Drug Administration sub-subseries material addresses the use of DES in animal feed, advisory notices sent to physicians, and other documents about DES regulation during the 1970s. The National Institutes of Health sub-subseries covers the DES Task Force reports --convened in 1979, and again in 1985--, the National Cancer Institute's long-term study named Diethylstilbestrol Adenosis (DESAD), and subsequent investigations. There are also Congressional hearings from both the House and the Senate concerning DES and its regulation in this subseries.
- SERIES VII. MEDICAL CORRESPONDENCE AND RESEARCH DATA (1979-2013), 0.63 linear feet
  In accordance with professional guidelines, the contents of this series have been restricted for twenty years and will be available to researchers in 2037. The material will then be subject to the same access agreement as the rest of the collection.
  This series contains information requests and medical problem reports from DES Action USA members and from the general public. The correspondence contains both personal identifying information, as well as personal health information for letter writers, as well as minor children and grandchildren. In addition, the series contains similar sensitive content in response to the third-generation health questionnaire found at the end of SERIES V. OUTREACH.
- SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS (1977-2011), 2.5 linear ft.
  This series is comprised of photographs and other audiovisual material, documenting the work and activities of DES Action USA. Materials include photograph albums, educational slides, public service announcements, as well as other material types. The subseries Photographs contains several photograph and scrapbook albums. Albums contain photographs and clippings of occasions such as board meetings, annual meetings, and local and regional activities of DES Action USA affiliates during the National DES Awareness Week in 1983. The late 1980s and 1990s are recorded in loose color photographs, arranged by event and date. There are also assorted media campaign photographs of flyers and DES-related images, as well as a set of publicity photographs of Jean Kasem. More about Kasem's work with DES Action USA can be found in SERIES II. MEMBERSHIP AND FINANCIAL MATERIALS.
  There are several sets of 35mm slides that are the counterparts to the scripts found in SERIES V. OUTREACH within the Medical Professionals subseries. The cassette that accompanies the 1980 "Ask Your Mother" talk is found in the following Audiotapes subseries. There are two other cassettes, a second slide show recording, and the series of public service announcements that actor Linda Kelsey recorded in 1982.
  The next subseries, CD-ROMs, contains the continuing medical education programs developed with the Centers for Disease Control and distributed by DES Action USA in 2003. There are also two CDs: one holds a copy of Pat Cody's original manuscript for her history of DES Action USA, and the second holds scans of Eli Lilly advertisements from 1957.
  The Videotapes subseries include public service announcements, news interviews, two films about DES (A Healthy Baby Girl and The Bitter Taste of a Miracle Drug), and two medical lecture recordings.
- SERIES IX. OVERSIZE MATERIAL (1984-2007), 1 linear ft.
  This series of oversize materials contains both artifacts and analog materials. There is a set of "Ask Your Mother" keychains from circa 1983 and a "Bad Karma for Big Pharma" t-shirt from 2007. The posters are from different outreach and awareness campaigns, and most are undated. In addition, there is one news article on oversize paper, from the 2003 Centers for Disease Control DES update campaign. See SERIES V. OUTREACH for more material on media campaigns, educational materials, and press coverage.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION
  - History
    - Coalition for the Medical Rights of Women, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - DES Action organizational history and timelines, 1978-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors
    - Internal correspondence, 1999-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Meetings
      - Minutes and reports, 1977-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6-12)
      - Minutes and reports, 1991-2014 (Box 2, Folder 1-12)
    - Policies
      - Manual, 1998, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
      - Ephemera from Manual binder, 1993-2005 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Meeting notes from Manual binder, 1990-2003 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Leadership
      - Christianson, Kari, 2005, 2010, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Cody, Nora, 2001, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Cody, Pat, 1979-2010, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Howell, Fran, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Organization
    - Articles of Incorporation, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Bylaws, 1980-1999 (Box 3, Folder 7-10)
    - Internal Revenue Service tax-exemption ruling, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Affiliate Groups
      - Bay Area (CA), 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Michigan, 1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Washington, D.C., 1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Policy and Procedures Handbook for affiliate groups, circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - DES Action Affiliate Manual, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Annual reports
      - 1977-2001 (Box 3, Folder 17-23)
- SERIES II. MEMBERSHIP AND FINANCIAL MATERIALS
  - Membership
    - Correspondence, 1988, 2006-2014 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    - Renewal letters, 1996-2005 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Fundraising
    - Special appeals
      - Letters, 1979-1996 (Box 4, Folder 9-13)
      - Letters, 1997-2014 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
      - Ideas, 1990-1993, 2006, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - 30th anniversary events, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Celebrity support
      - Kasem, Jean: correspondence 1990-1992, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Kasem, Jean: ephemera, 1991-1992, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Grants
      - Foundation grants, 1990, 2013, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Proposal to March of Dimes, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - DES Action USA profile for funders, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
- SERIES III. LEGISLATION AND LITIGATION
  - Federal legislation
    - National DES Awareness Week, 1985 [See also scrapbook, VIII] (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Slaughter, Louise M.
      - DES Education and Research Amendments of 1992 (H.R. 4178), 1990-1994, undated (Box 5, Folder 13-16)
      - DES Education and Research Amendments of 1992, 1992 October-December (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
      - Senate counterpart bills S. 208 and S. 2837, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Women's Health Office Act of 1995 (H.R.1736), May 8, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Product Liability Fairness Act of 1995 (H.R.956), 1996 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Women's Health Research and Prevention Amendments of 1998, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Lobbying
      - Guide, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Visits, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - State legislation
    - Alaska, 1996 May 22-28 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - California, 1980-1982 [See also NCCP 1980-84) (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - New York, 1980, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Litigation
  - Mink v. University of Chicago, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Bichler v. Eli Lilly and Co., 1979 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - DES Action USA Litigation Information Sheet, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Levine, Aaron
    - Correspondence and press coverage, 1984, 2001-2007 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Case rulings and correspondence, 2005-2010 (Box 6, Folder 16-19)
    - Amicus curiae brief in Wyeth v. Levine, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - London, Michael, circa 2008 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Shainwald, Sybil, 2005-2010 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- SERIES IV. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS
  - DES Action annual meetings [SEE ALSO SERIES IX. PHOTOGRAPHS]
    - Annual meeting ephemera, reports, and transcripts, 1988-1999 (Box 7, Folder 3-6)
  - Research conferences
    - National Institute of Environmental and Health Sciences Symposium on Estrogens in the Environment, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Meeting on DES-Related Research, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - United Nations Conference on Women's Health, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - National Institutes of Health Workshop: Long-term effects of exposure to diethylstilbestrol (DES), 1992 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - DES Research Update 1999: Current Knowledge, Future Directions, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - DES Action International Colloquium: Discovery, Education, Science
      - Colloquium planning, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Colloquium materials, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Colloquium transcripts, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- SERIES V. OUTREACH
  - Health education contracts
    - Northern California Cancer Project, 1978-1982
      - Committee for the Medical Rights of Women pilot contract, 1978-1982 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - DES Action contract for media campaign and outreach, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      - Informational literature, 1978, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      - Community organizing manuals, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 18-19)
      - Informational literature, 1981, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - California state contract, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - California state campaign press kit, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - National Cancer Institute
    - Massachusetts, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Centers for Disease Control DES Update Campaign
    - DES National Educational Campaign: findings from formative research report, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    - Campaign planning and contract records, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence with affiliate groups, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - DES Action USA Affiliate Tool Kit, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Press releases and news articles, 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - CDC's DES Update Teleconference Series, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - CDC's DES Update book, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - CDC's DES Update educational literature, 2002-2003 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Public
    - Media campaigns
      - DES Awareness, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 14)
        - Defeat the Product Liability Act, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 15)
        - Ask Your Mother, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 16)
        - Talking to your mother about drugs (PA), 2004 (Box 8, Folder 17)
        - Press releases, 1990-1994 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Press coverage
      - Press releases, 1998, 2000, undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
      - Letters to the editor, 1983, 1994, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Articles, 1971-2012 (Box 9, Folder 2-6)
    - Educational literature
      - DES exposure questionnaires (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Information packet for inquirers (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Information sheets (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Order forms (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Publishing graphics, 1957-1984, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - "Working together", 1985 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Ephemera
        - Booklets, 1980-1983 (Box 9, Folder 13)
        - Booklet, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 14)
        - Booklet, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 15)
        - Brochures, 1975-1977 (Box 9, Folder 16)
        - Brochures, 1978-1980 (Box 9, Folder 17)
        - Brochures, 1981-1984 (Box 9, Folder 18)
        - Brochures, 1995, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Government publications
        - 1976-1980 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        - 1981-1986, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
        - National Cancer Institute booklets, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Related organizations' publications
        - Literature from other women's health organizations, 1976-1992, 1997, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Publications
      - DES Action Voice newsletter
        - Institutional subscriptions to DES Action Voice, 1999-2002 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        - Issue 122 editorial materials, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        - Medical literature index for DES Action Voice, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        - Issues 1-97, 1978-2003 (Box 10, Folder 8-13)
        - Issues 98-141, 148-49, 2003-2014, 2016 (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
    - Writing by DES Action USA members
      - DES Stories Project (Box 11)
        - DES Stories correspondence and publicity, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - DES Stories book, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - DES Voices book project
        - Background research materials, 1974-2005 (Box 11, Folder 6-10)
        - DES Action USA book draft, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 11)
        - Reprinting licenses, 2007-2008 (Box 11, Folder 12)
        - Design and publication, 2008 (Box 11, Folder 13)
        - DES Voices: From Anger to Action, 2008 (Box 11, Folder 14)
        - Essays, 1975-2003, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
      - Medical information requests-anonymized, 1982-2000, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Medical professionals
    - History of the D.E.S. Controversy: News Clippings 1945-1988, circa 1989 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Provider education
      - Booklets, 1976-1986, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
      - DES Action slideshow script, 1984 [see also slides] (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Nurse education script, 1985 [see also slides] (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Physician education script, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Epidemiology curriculum project, 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Clinical reviews, 1990-2001 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Curriculum module, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Survey research
      - Third-generation survey development, 1999-2004 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Health history survey questionnaire and results, 2012-2014 (Box 12, Folder 15)
- SERIES VI. DIETHYLSTILBESTROL SUBJECT FILES
  - Consumer health
    - Public Citizen reports, 1972-1985 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Medical research
    - Bibliography by DES Action USA, circa 1980-2003 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Bibliography by Aaron Levine, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Diethylstilbestrol medication names, 1981-1990 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Diethylstilbestrol prescribing information sheets, 1961, 1988, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Medical quotations concerning estrogen use by DES daughters, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Research articles, 1939-81 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Third-generation research, 1978-2006, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Pharmaceutical companies
    - Investigational drug Gestiva (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - DES advertisements, 1953, 1957, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Eli Lilly advertisements, 1945-1952, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Eli Lilly's Dirty Tricks, 1985-2001, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Protest of Eli Lilly-sponsored Achievement Awards in Women's Health, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 13-15)
  - Federal government
    - Department of Health, Education and Welfare
      - Food and Drug Administration
        - Diethylstilbestrol, 1973-1978 (Box 13, Folder 16)
        - Physician advisory, 1977-1979 (Box 13, Folder 17)
        - Withdrawal of approval for animal feed use, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - National Institutes of Health
        - National Cancer Institute diethylstilbestrol adenosis (DESAD) request for proposals, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 19)
        - National Cancer Institute diethylstilbestrol adenosis (DESAD) study, 1976-1990, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 1)
        - DES Task Force Summary Report, 1978 September 21 (Box 14, Folder 2)
        - DES Task Force correspondence and reports, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 3)
        - National Cancer Institute DES Follow-Up study, 1993-1999 ==United States Congress (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - House of Representatives
        - Regulation of Diethylstilbestrol (DES), 1972 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Senate
        - Testimony from committee hearings, 1973, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- SERIES VII. MEDICAL INFORMATION AND RESEARCH DATA [RESTRICTED UNTIL 1 JAN 2037]
  - Correspondence
    - Medical concerns, 1979-2006 (Box 15, Folder 1-24)
    - Medical concerns, 2007-2013, undated (Box 16, Folder 1-6)
  - Query and survey responses
    - Health problem reports, 2003 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Mother and daughter stories, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Third-generation cases, 1983-2005 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Third-generation survey, 2003 (Box 16, Folder 10-12)
    - Pathology reports, 2009 (Box 16, Folder 13)
- SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
  - Photographs
    - Albums
      - First board meeting spoof album, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - National DES Awareness Week scrapbook, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 2-4)
      - "DES Action 1979-" album, 1981-1987 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Events
      - Annual meeting, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Board meeting, May 1988 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Annual meeting, October 1988 (Box 18, Folder 3-8)
      - Annual meeting, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 9-10)
      - Annual meeting, 1994 (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
      - DES Research Update prints and negatives, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - DES Research Update digital prints on 31/4" floppy, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - DES Research Update prints, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Photographs from media campaigns, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Kasem, Jean, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Slides
    - DES: The Wonder Drug slides and transparencies, circa 1980 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - DES Action slideshow for health professionals, 1980 (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Ask Your Mother slideshow instructions, 1980 (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - Ask Your Mother slideshow, 1980 (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Slide Set IV, DES daughter cervices, undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - Updated slides, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Audiotapes [Access copies needed]
    - Kelsey, Linda -- DES Action PSAs, 1983 February 3 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Your Mother--Finding the DES Exposed slideshow audio (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - DES Action - "Ask your Mother" - slide tape show for health workers [Master 1985] (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Digital Media [Access copies needed]
    - CDC's DES Update: Educational Tools for Health Care Providers, 2003, CD (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
    - Pat's Book July 2006, CD-R (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - 1957 DES advertisement scans, CD-R (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Videotapes [Access copies needed]
    - DES Action PSAs :10/:20/:30/:45/:60 U.S. Version (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - DES Action PSA American Version 30 sec, 1988 March 25 (Box 21, Folder 2-3)
    - DES Action PSAs-3 by Linda Kelsey 1982, 5 by Jean Kasem (10,20,30,45 and 60 sec) (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - DES Good Morning America 1992 April 22 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Representative Louise Slaughter [Tape 3 VR# 16) 40:33, 1992 June 8 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Representative Louise Slaughter [Tape 4 VR# 17) 40:33, 1992 June 8 (Box 22, Folder 7)